<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: daemon | No F*cking Idea]]></title>
  <link href="http://no-fucking-idea.com/blog/categories/daemon/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://no-fucking-idea.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-25T19:37:27+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://no-fucking-idea.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jakub Oboza]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[jakub.oboza@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to use twitter for something else than pics of cats]]></title>
    <link href="http://no-fucking-idea.com/blog/2013/06/09/how-to-use-twitter-for-something-else-than-pics-of-cats/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-09T23:30:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://no-fucking-idea.com/blog/2013/06/09/how-to-use-twitter-for-something-else-than-pics-of-cats</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So it was long since last post and i have in pipeline many posts on ODM&rsquo;s, Genetic Algorithms, Streaming Algorithms Clojure and Haskell i was working on but nothing is finished ;/. Need time!</p>

<h1>I&rsquo;m using twitter</h1>

<p>And most of the time it is just updates from friends, sometimes some news from hacker world that potentially could be interesting. I use twitter in a bit odd way first of all i post link to things i read during commute to work :) and i use twitter to post alters from my apps to me.</p>

<h1>Why twitter ?</h1>

<p>I think twitter is great because he is posting things to my phone also, so instead of building this really complex infrastructure i can use twitter to do everything.</p>

<h1>How ?</h1>

<p>This is simple i add to every app i make a bit of code to handle twitter. eg. method like this in ruby</p>

<p>``` ruby</p>

<pre><code>def alert_notify!
  if @config[:notification_list]
    notifier = Twitter::Client.new(
      :oauth_token =&gt; @config[:"oauth_token"],
      :oauth_token_secret =&gt; @config[:"oauth_token_secret"]
    )
    @config[:notification_list].each do |entry|
      notifier.direct_message_create(entry, "#{Time.now}: I crushed! please go to logs and see what happpened!")
    end
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>```
This is part of TwitterDriver/Agent class. And i wrap everything into exception handler when i get exception i log it and send notification to me via twitter direct message.</p>

<p>I love this way of using twitter because a year ago i thought it is only for sharing very random not useful messages about cats and sharing instagram pictures.</p>

<p>Try it yourself!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
