<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: doge | No F*cking Idea]]></title>
  <link href="http://no-fucking-idea.com/blog/categories/doge/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://no-fucking-idea.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-25T19:37:27+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://no-fucking-idea.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jakub Oboza]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[jakub.oboza@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dogecoin mining on raspberry pi LOLMODE]]></title>
    <link href="http://no-fucking-idea.com/blog/2014/01/14/dogecoin-mining-on-raspberry-pi-lolmode/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-14T10:43:36+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://no-fucking-idea.com/blog/2014/01/14/dogecoin-mining-on-raspberry-pi-lolmode</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>!!!UPDATE:
Download cpuminer and build from tar <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/cpuminer/">http://sourceforge.net/projects/cpuminer/</a> git HEAD is broken and will not let you run configure.</p>

<p>If you have <code>800 Mhash/s</code> GPU (Graphics card) i&rsquo;m sure you often think about making your raspberry pi a dogecoin miner. Because why not :D ? It is not effective i warn you :) you will get around <code>0.34 khash/s</code> that is about 2000 times less than your GPU :) and about 500 times less than CPU on your box. But its easy and fun.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/83LnzuU.jpg" alt="doge meme" /></p>

<p>I mainly did it for fun to see how it will react, work and what is the possible heat problem.</p>

<h1>Again Why ?</h1>

<p>Because DOGE, doge coin is THE NEW BLACK. Its future! An Irony on all crypto currency :) and its value is based on meme, laugh and happiness. This is much better than bitcoin :> at least for me</p>

<h1>Connect to your raspberry pi</h1>

<p>You will need:
<code>bash requirements
  λ automake
  λ gcc
  λ git-core
  λ libcurl
</code></p>

<p>if you are using like me <code>2014-01-07-wheezy-raspbian</code> raspbian you will have everything ready :) one thing to install is <code>automake</code> and you can do this by typing <code>apt-get update</code>  followed by <code>apt-get install automake</code> this is all you need.</p>

<p>lets get on the box! (default login/passowrd for this image is pi:raspberry)
<code>bash
10:54 kuba@pc12:~ λ ssh pi@192.168.1.22
pi@raspberrypi ~ $
</code>
(This ip address is just an example :D you will need to have a way to find it in your network.)</p>

<p>Now all you need to do is to clone CPU miner for it.</p>

<p><code>bash
git clone https://github.com/pooler/cpuminer.git
</code></p>

<p>This will download your mining software on the raspeberry pi, next we need to compile it and run!</p>

<p><code>bash compiling
pi@raspberrypi ~/Workspace $ cd cpuminer-2.3.2/
pi@raspberrypi ~/Workspace/cpuminer-2.3.2 $
./autogen.sh
... script will take some time ...
./configure CFLAGS="-O3"
make
</code>
This will compile and build the minerd binary that is ready to start mining :). Well you need to do one thing, join a doge pool. I&rsquo;m not gone go into details of solo mining vs pool minnig :)  i&rsquo;m just a simple miner :D</p>

<p>If you need more info on mining pools you should check this topic <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/dogecoin/comments/1tn8yz/dogecoin_mining_pool_list/">http://www.reddit.com/r/dogecoin/comments/1tn8yz/dogecoin_mining_pool_list/</a></p>

<p>I personally at the time of writing this post i&rsquo;m using small pool called chunky pool :).</p>

<h2>Starting to mine!</h2>

<p>Now we have software lets actually mine something :).
You will need to create a shell script that will start minerd on your raspberry pi. My looks like this</p>

<p><code>bash run.sh
./minerd --a scrypt --threads 1 -o stratum+tcp://pool.chunky.ms:3333 -O dogedogedoge.pi:password
</code></p>

<p>make it executable and run! Yay you are a dogecoin farmer now! CPU mining is not the most optimal but hey..its all just for lolz :)</p>

<h3>Heat problems ?</h3>

<p>For me 2 hours of mining on raspberry pi did not generate any extra heat or stuff like this, seems to be stable. I was worried it will got nuts on this topic but i was proven wrong.</p>

<h1>Summay</h1>

<p>This sucks in terms of speed, you will get close to none speed because below 2 khash/s its not even worth it, you will not be on any stats on any pool even listed, periodically you will actually hit the jackpot and get a success pimping you to 2khash/s for about 60 sec but that is  just a lie, you scored a win and this will give you some parts of doge. Last i checked you were able to get around 0.67 doge per hour of your raspberry time. That is really really bad as pretty basic GPU pimps you to 600+</p>

<p>Cheers :) Hope it helps! Much fun, so currency.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
